<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Pacquet of intelligence from New-Providence in the province of the Bahama Islands in America in two parts wherein the miserable state of the said province and people inhabiting the same for the space of four years under the tyranny of an indigent, debauch'd idiot and most pernicious villain named Cadwallader Jones is briefly demonstrated in letters of complaint against him to Coll. Phillip Ludwell, gouvernour of Carolina ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54389</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">7944497</idno>
  <idno type="VID">40621</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248540844</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P156A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24050</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">07944497</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54389)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1211:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Pacquet of intelligence from New-Providence in the province of the Bahama Islands in America in two parts wherein the miserable state of the said province and people inhabiting the same for the space of four years under the tyranny of an indigent, debauch'd idiot and most pernicious villain named Cadwallader Jones is briefly demonstrated in letters of complaint against him to Coll. Phillip Ludwell, gouvernour of Carolina ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Bahamas --  History --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40621:1"/>
            <p>A Pacquet of Intelligence FROM NEW-PROVIDENCE▪ In the Province of the <hi>BAHAMA</hi> Islands, in AMERICA, In Two PARTS.</p>
            <p>Wherein, the Miserable State of the said Province and People In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting the same, for the space of Four Years, under the Tyranny of an Indigent Debauch'd Idiot, and most pernicious Villain, Named Cadwallader Jones: Is briefly Demonstrated, in LETTERS of Complaint against him, to Coll. Phillip Ludwell, GOUERNOUR of CAROLINA Whose Letter (as an Answer) herein is Incerted. And also, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stract of a Letter from Mr. <hi>Josias Clark,</hi> on the same Theme.</p>
            <p>The Royal Preacher (among the Evils that he had observed under the Sun) Notes this for one, <hi>viz. Folley set in place of Great Dignity.</hi> Ecles. 10. 5, 6. The Evil whereof hath a double Aspect, <hi>viz.</hi> I. On the Person so dignified, as to the <hi>Indecorum</hi> of it, <hi>Because Honour is not seemly for a Fool.</hi> Prov. 26. 1. II. On the People over whom he is so placed. <hi>Because the Governour that lacketh Ʋnderstanding, is a great Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor.</hi> Prov. 28. 16. <hi>And surely Oppression maketh a Wise Man Mad.</hi> Ecles. 7. 7. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (for the Administration of Government) <hi>Better is a Poor and wise Child, then an Old and Foolish Man, who will no more be Admonished:</hi> Ecles. 4, 13.</p>
            <p>Printed Chiefly for Information of the Lords Proprietors of both the said Provinces: And Published to Illustrate the present happiness of the People Inhabiting this Island of Great <hi>Brttain,</hi> under the Government of our Glorious and Gracious King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> III. Who is the great Restorer of our Laws [as to the free and equal Administration thereof] where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Lives, Liberties, and Properties, are Rescued from being a Prey to the Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lusts of Wicked Rulers, <hi>Who</hi> (by the Wisest of Kings) <hi>are compared to Roaring</hi> Lyons, <hi>and Ranging</hi> Bears. Prov. 28. 15. The Truth whereof, hath been Eminently Exemplified in the said <hi>Cadwallader Jones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author. 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:40621:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40621:2"/>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The CASE of <hi>Thomas Bulkley,</hi> late of <hi>New Providence,</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, briefly represented to the Right Honourable the Lords of His Majesties Councel of TRADE.</head>
               <p>THE said <hi>Bulkley,</hi> (for his <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Zealous Activity</hi> in the Discharge of his Bounden Duty to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. to the <hi>Lords Proprietors</hi> of the <hi>Provinces</hi> of <hi>Carolina,</hi> and the <hi>Bahama</hi> Islands in <hi>America,</hi> and to His Majesties Subjects Inhabiting the first named <hi>Province,</hi> in the Accusation and Prosecution of <hi>Cadwallader Jones,</hi> late Governour of the said Islands, who was a Wicked <hi>Tyrant, Traytor, Murtherer, Felonious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirator,</hi> confederate with <hi>Pirates, Burglarious Robber,</hi> and Guilty of other <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Misdemeanours,</hi> contained in sundry <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Accusation</hi> Exhibited against him▪) Under the said <hi>Jones</hi>'s <hi>Ʋsurped Power</hi> (being Rescued out of Custody) hath been <hi>Barbarously</hi> Imprisoned 485 days, without any lawful Cause alledged by the Accuser upon his Oath, or the Testimony of any Witnesses; And in the said term of his <hi>Imprisonment,</hi> his House, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therein, hath sundry times been <hi>Broke</hi> open in a <hi>Felonious</hi> manner, by <hi>Armed Pirates.,</hi> Instigated to the doing thereof by the said Rescued <hi>Criminal,</hi> and his <hi>Trayterous Complices,</hi> the Principal whereof was <hi>John Graves,</hi> who was the <hi>False</hi> and <hi>Malicious</hi> accuser of the said <hi>Bulkley.</hi> The <hi>Affrightments</hi> of which <hi>Burglarious Assaults</hi> on the House, were the cause of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsion Fits, Painful Languishing Sickness,</hi> and finally of <hi>Death,</hi> to the said <hi>Bulkleys</hi> Wife. By all which <hi>Monsterous</hi> dealings of the said <hi>Jones, Graves,</hi> &amp;c. the said <hi>Bulkley</hi> has lost his Virtuous Wife (<hi>Barbarously Murthered</hi>) by the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glarious Assaults</hi> of <hi>Pyratical Ruffians;</hi> His own Health by <hi>Extream hard and Long Imprisonment,</hi> his <hi>Reputation</hi> by <hi>False</hi> and <hi>Malicious Accusation</hi> of <hi>High Treason,</hi> his <hi>Traffick</hi> and <hi>Commerce,</hi> as a <hi>Merchant,</hi> has been wholly <hi>Confounded,</hi> and his <hi>Estate</hi> Wasted in Extravagant Expences, occasion'd by his <hi>Wifes Sickness,</hi> and his own <hi>Imprisonment,</hi> and by other <hi>Losses</hi> and <hi>Damages</hi> amounting to the, value of <hi>Four Thousand Pounds;</hi> for Reparation whereof, and Condign Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those <hi>Miscreants,</hi> who were the <hi>Authors, Abettors, Actors,</hi> and <hi>Acces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sories.</hi> He hath apply'd himself to the Succeeding <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Bahama</hi> Islands, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Nicholas Trott,</hi> and to the <hi>Lords Proprietors Ministers of Justice</hi> at <hi>Carolina,</hi> who having all of them denyed him the benefit of the <hi>Laws</hi> (which are said to be the <hi>Birth Right</hi> of every <hi>English Man</hi>) he hath been Constrained to leave the place of his Settled Habitation, <hi>Lands, Houses, Goods,</hi> and <hi>Debts</hi> there, being of great Value, and to Travel from thence 3000 Miles over the Seas in coming to <hi>England,</hi> where he hath spent two Years in <hi>Addressing</hi> to, and <hi>Attending</hi> on the <hi>Lords Proprietors,</hi> who have been so <hi>Ʋngenerous,</hi> as to <hi>Disregard</hi> his <hi>Meritorious Services,</hi> and <hi>Matchless Sufferings;</hi> and so <hi>unjust</hi> as to <hi>Reject</hi> his most <hi>reasonable Propositious,</hi> viz. <hi>That they would put him into such a post of Authority and Power as may inable him to have the benefit of the Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all those in their said Provences, who have done Irrepairable Wrongs to the said</hi> Bulkley; <hi>and also against all those who have denyed him Justice against them, contrary to the Duty of their Offices, and the obligation of their Oaths, for Dispenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Justice freely and imparcialy to all the Kings Subjects, suing for it in the Limits of their Jurisdictions.</hi> And seeing there hath been a total <hi>failure of Justice</hi> in all the <hi>Derivative Channels,</hi> the said <hi>Bulkley</hi> now repairs to the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> of it, which is a <hi>Living Spring,</hi> from whence it doth and shall ever <hi>flow</hi> to the <hi>Relief</hi> of all His Majesties <hi>Oppressed</hi> and agrieved <hi>Subjects,</hi> of whom, none have Served him more <hi>Loyally, Dilligently,</hi> and <hi>Constantly,</hi> nor <hi>suffer'd</hi> for so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as hath the said <hi>Thomas Bulkley,</hi> who hath not only Sustained the Losses and Damages aforesaid, but thereby for the space of Five Years hath been and still is out of all manner of <hi>Profitable Employment,</hi> whereby to Maintain himself and his Off-spring: In which deplorable Condition for Relief, he hath Petition'd to, and now humbly depends on his Most Just, Generous, and Merciful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King, in whose Service he will esteem it his greatest Terrestial Honour and Happiness to Spend the Residue of his Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:40621:3"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40621:3"/>
               <head>A LETTER from <hi>Gilbert Ashley,</hi> and <hi>Bowen Clasen,</hi> Esqs; (being Deputies to two of the Lords Proprietors of the Province of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolina,</hi> and the <hi>Bahama</hi> Islands) and <hi>Thomas Bulkley,</hi> Secretary of the last Named Province. Superscribed, To the Honourable Collonel <hi>Phillip Ludwell,</hi> Governour of <hi>Carolina.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>WEE the Subscribers (by Mr.</hi> William Baker, <hi>owner of a Bark which Arriv'd here, from</hi> South Carolina <hi>the</hi> 13th <hi>instant) having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived some general, but very imperfect Information of your being come thither, with Authority from the Lords Proprietors, of that, and this Colony, either to be Chief Governour, or at least to inquire into the conduct of Publick Affairs in both, and to Reform what your Wisdom shall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to need; Do with all Humble Deference, Congratulate your safe Arrival there, and earnestly wish for the same here: Wee (tho less considerable) standing in as much need of your Authority, and Wisdom to rectifie our most disorderly Government. We think not fit to Anticipate you with our Complaints, and the Causes thereof, which are many, and great; whereby a hopeful Settlement of these their Lordships Dominions, [capable of great Improvements] is not only much retarded, but almost ruin'd. We (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the duty of our several Places and Stations) have used our best Endeavours that such Laws and Ordinances might be Made, and Executed, as in our Judgments tended most to the Honour and Profit of our Masters, and general good of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and People: But to our grief, we find all Laws for the Suppression of Vice, and Incouragement of Virtue and Industry, either Opposed in the making, or Ennervated in the Execution, the Lords Interest wholy disregarded: and those who are most Zealous to promote it, Discountenanced, the publick Treasure secretly and unaccountably consum'd; all Sober, Virtuous, and Industrious Persons Abhor'd: Privateers and Pirates, and such like Dissolute and Debauch'd persons Favoured, and thereby made Impudently Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. In this deplorable case we are wholy destitute of a remedy, within our selves; for General Assemblies above all things are hated and dreaded▪ And those who Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their Calling, and Sitting, termed Trattors; and when Summon'd, the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions defeated by packed Elections, of the most unfit, and unworthy Persons to be Members. And if that will not fully confound all Designs and Endeavours for publick good, then self-conceited King</hi> Solomon, <hi>or (more properly) King</hi> Bramble, <hi>will be sure to effect it, by his refusal to pass such Bills into Acts. But the Soveraign Balsom of your Power and Prudence, (which we have a great Character of) if seasonably applyed, may heal our Death Threatning Distempers. To you therefore, as our Extraordinary Political Physitian, we look and call for a speedy visit; the hopes whereof, is a Reviving Cordial to your Afflicted Patients, who will be (as oppertunity offers) Your Faithful and Humble Servants,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>New Providence, <date>July <hi>the 16th</hi> 1692</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Gilbert Ashley.</item>
                        <item>Bowen Clasen.</item>
                        <item>Thomas Bulkley.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="response">
               <head>An Answer to the foregoing Letter, Directed as followeth. <hi>These, For</hi> Gilbert Ashley, Bowen Clasen, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Bulkley, <hi>Esqs: Or to any one of them, at</hi> Providence.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Masters,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAD I had any oppertunity, I had long ere this returned you an Answer to yours of the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> received from Mr. <hi>Clark:</hi> I am very sorry both for the Lords, and your own sakes, to find such great Discords between you and your Governour; and should be extreamly glad if I could contribute any thing to a Reconciliation.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40621:4"/>
               <p>In order to which, I would very willingly have taken a Journey to you▪ if my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs would have permitted▪ and having so Rational Persons, as I have reason to believe you have amongst you, to treat withal▪ should not have dispaired of a good Effect.</p>
               <p>I have considered the contents of your Letter, which tho in some part to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, may seem something too Passionate; yet I fear in general, there is too much reason to believe the Complaints are not wholy without cause.</p>
               <p>I have known your Governour several years, and altho perhaps he may be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a stranger to those Polliticks, which are requisite for the Well and Peaceable Ordering of a Government; yet he being of a generous and good Nature (which he has always past for) I think it a little strange that he should be so utterly Uncouncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, by those of more acquaintance with the place, and joyned in power with him.</p>
               <p>At the same time I received yours, I received a Letter also from him, near the same date, with complaints on his side; but neither he, nor you, give me the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of eithers Grievances. I have discoursed with Dr. <hi>Clark,</hi> who I believe has given me what Light he can, which yet cannot lead me to find out clearly where the Shooe pincheth, but (by what I guess) if it were possible for me to come to you, with any manner of Security to their Lordships Affairs here, at this present, I should not much doubt to settle all to your satisfaction; but the trouble I have met with here, will not yet admit my least absence. I'se asure you my desires are great to it, but since I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do as I would, if you please to follow my Advice, I am in hopes (by Gods Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) I may do you some Service.</p>
               <p>My Advice is, That you meet alltogether, and draw up an Impartial account of all matters, <hi>viz.</hi> The Grievances the Countrey (or you for them) complain of on the one side; and what the Governour has to complain of, on the other side: and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party do communicate to the other, what is drawn up, that if any mistake be, it may be rectified by consent on either side, before you send it away. I have also now made the same proposal to the Governour, who (I suppose) will not refuse it, if he do, I shall have no very good opinion of his Cause, or Judgment.</p>
               <p>If you think fit to do this, and send it me as soon as possibly you can; I have very great confidence I should Even the matters of Variance that are between you, or leave one side or tother without excuse. However, If I should not be so happy in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation at the first dash, it would be no great prejudice or loss of time to either, since the affairs of the Countrey (I mean as to the defence of it against a Common Enemy, or Judicial proceedings on Civil Actions between Man, and Man) may go on.</p>
               <p>But as to any manner of Process for any Heats, or Piques, which are (by either part) taken to be Misdemeanours in the Government, I do Earnestly Exhort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you all, that it do cease, till the whole matter have been enquired into.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, if an Accomodation be Effected, I shall think my self very happy, in having done the Lords, and the Country, so good a Service. I hope you will all set heartily about it, considering the well or ill-being of every Person in the Country de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon it: For I hope you all take the Authority of him, to be Infallible, that tells you, <hi>A House divided within it self cannot stand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall trouble you no further at present, but asure you of my readiness to do you Service, being</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>South Carolina,</hi>
                     <date>Octob. 27th 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  <signed>your Affectionate Friend and Humble Servand. Phill. Ludwell.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE Governour speaks of an Act of</hi> Indemnity▪ <hi>which he refused to Pass, pray let me have a true Coppy of it. I have also written to the Governour for a Coppy, but desire it from you also. If nothing will do, but my coming, that shall not be wanting, as soon as ever I can settle matters here, which I hope are now in a fair way: But I hope you will all see your Interest so well, that there will be no need of my coming; unless it be to Rejoyce with you, for your good Fortune.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pray send me the true grounds of the Differences between the Governour, and You.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours as above. P. L.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40621:4"/>
               <head>An Abstract of a LETTER from Mr. <hi>Josias Clark,</hi> at <hi>South-Carrolina:</hi> Superscribed, To <hi>Thomas Bulkley,</hi> Esq; at the Island of <hi>New-Providence.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis is the first opportunity of Writing to you, that I have met with, since my Arival here; but you will find (by the Governours Letters to your self, and Friends, and to Coll.</hi> Jones) <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> I have not forgot the Gratitude which I owe to you, for the constant Kindness you shewed me, during my Residence in, and at my Departure from</hi> Providence, <hi>as also since my Arival here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have very fairly stated the case of your Government, to his Honour here, tho wanting Authentick Evidence for the matters of Fact. He referves the Determination, till he receives the account of things from your selves, and then I doubt not but the Decision will be just and speedy: Except your Governo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and you, think fit to be reconciled before, which his Honour here Heartily Wishes, for your own S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes, and Exhorts you both unto. (For I have seen his Letters) And it is my oppinion that it is your wisest Course; but if Coll.</hi> Jones <hi>be Intractable, and Irreconcilable, he will soon smart for his Folley.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>Sir, My tenderest Respects and Service to your self, your good Lady, Coll.</hi> Bowen Clasen, <hi>Mr.</hi> Ashley, <hi>and all others, who retaine any Friendship for (Sir,)</hi>
                  </salute>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your most Affectionate and Zealous Servant,</hi> Josias Clark.</signed>
                  <dateline>Charles Town <hi>in</hi> Carolina. <date>Novemb. <hi>7th.</hi> 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Second LETTER to the said Collonel</hi> Phillip Ludwell, <hi>Governour of</hi> Carolina, <hi>being a Replication to his Answer to the first, to him Written, by the said</hi> Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Clasen, <hi>and</hi> Bulkley.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE <hi>24th.</hi> of the last Month (by Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi>) we received yours, Dated the <hi>27th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> wherein your Honour abounds in Expressions of Kindness and Condescention to us; and a compassionate Resentment of our Divisions and Discords, and the evil tendency thereof: As also declaring your readiness to Engage your self to Promote and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish a Reconciliation between us, in hopes whereof you expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s your self willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a Voyage hither; for which Favours we want words to express our Humble Gratitude. By yours we are inform'd, your Honour hath received ours of the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> in which (as your Honour speaks) some things to a stranger may seem too passionate: But truly Sir, they do but seem so, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o any other then a stranger, we might say as <hi>David</hi> to his Brother <hi>Eliah, is there not a Cause,</hi> and that not Personal or Private, but Publick and General, wherein no less than the whose Interest of the Lords Proprietors, safety and Tranquillity of the people Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting these their Lordships Territories, is involved. Your Honour faith that you have known our Governour several Years, and that he hath always past for a person of a Generous and good Nature, if he did, it was only as Counterfit Coine, till it is discovered; or else he is strangely Debased: For now, there does not appear in him one spark of true Generosity, nor so much as the Reliques thereof, but a Degenerate Ignoble Spirit, almost daily discovering it self, in Speeches and Actions Similar; whereof numerous Instances might be given. You say you have received Complaints from him also, but neither he nor we have given the particulars of each others Grievances. Sir, As we said before, the cause of our Complaints is not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Affronts and Injuries (which have been many and great) but for them we should not (at least by Letter) have troubled your Honour with our Complaints, but of as general a Nature as before is said, <hi>viz.</hi> The grand Charge we have against him, is great in it self, and great in respect of the many great ones contain'd in it: The general is that from the first of his coming hither, He hath managed a wicked design to set up Arbitrary and Tyrannical Government, not bounded nor regulated by Laws, but such as should be the Dictates of his own will, for serving the Corrupt Interests and Lusts of himself, and his Lewd and Beggerly Favourites; who were designed to Repair their decay'd Fortunes (become so by their own Vicious and Extravagant Courses) by Subjecting the People in their Bodies and Purces to their absolute Dominion and Avarice. The withstanding of which Designs, first in a regular and Parliamentary way, and when that proved Ineffectual, we were constrained (being at so great a distance from the Lords Proprietors) to use Extraordinary means to bring him to some better terms, which were Reasonable, Just, and Mild: To which, tho he then Conceded, and made many fair promises, yet in a little time (after the Muzle was off) he began to Act like a Beast of Prey again; and so hath continued to do, to this present time. I shall briefly give you Honour a view of some of his many Irregularities in Government.</p>
               <p n="1">I. He presumed to Refuse taking the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy to their Majesties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> having (as may without breach of Charity be suppos'd) some hopes of a Change of the Sceen in <hi>England,</hi> by King <hi>James</hi>'s Re▪ mounting the Throne again.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40621:5"/>II. He takes upon him to Dispence with the Lords Proprietors Instructions, contain'd in the <hi>4th.</hi> Paragraph thereof, wherein he is required to Summon a General Assembly, or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he did not, (upon a false pretence.) But instead of a Parliament, he constituted a Council consisting of himself, three Deputies, and four others, Chosen by the People, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentitives of them; with whose Advise and Consent he sell to making of Laws, to be of equall Authority and Force, with Acts of a General Assembly, till the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>December</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which was near six Months from the time of his Arrival.</p>
               <p n="3">III. He ordained himself to be Treasurer, and having so done, he presseth the Council to Levy a Tax on the people (who were then few and poor) for Building a new Fort, which if it had proceeded according to his projection, would have cost at least 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Whereas there was at that time an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Fort, which (tho gon to decay) with a small Charge would have been more Servic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able than the New one, which hath cost (as is supposed) about 100 <hi>l.</hi> and is no Defence.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. He gets a <hi>French</hi> Vessel, in which a parcel of Privateers had been Roveing and playing the Pirates, some parts whereof, he purchased of the Company (as was said) and most given him by the Company, yet (out of a Bravado) he gives out that she was taken by his Son, (being Captain of the Ship <hi>Jones</hi> came in from <hi>England</hi>) as a Lawful Prize of War: So he Erects a Court of Admiralty, for Tryal, and Condemnation of the said Ship, which being done, he Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses her to Sale by Inch of Candle; and useth effectual means that she might not be bought out of their Hands; so according to their design and desire, she was bought at a low rate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 42 <hi>l.</hi> whereas she was well worth 500 <hi>l.</hi> So that this Lumping peniworth might be their own, Two Thirds of the said Vessel, (as belonging to the Lord Proprietors and himself) was Sold to his Son, and One Third he allowed him as a Reward for his Valour in taking her. So the Lords are Fobb'd off with 14 <hi>l.</hi> for their Interest in the said Vessel, whereof his said Son he made Commander. I should proceed, but I find that such a Progre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve Narrative, would In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gross too much time, and swell too big to be contained in a Letter. I shall therefore send you some Papers, which (tho defective) will in some measure inable you to make a Judgment of him and his course and Actions: The Papers I have sent you, are the <hi>1st 2d.</hi> and <hi>3d.</hi> Speeches of our King <hi>Solomon,</hi> (to his first Parliament) for to him, he hath Preusmptuously compared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, in all things (Riches excepted) wherein his great Wisdom, Piety, Eloquence, and strength of Reasoning, doth Iminently appear: You will also see how hansomly he Princes it, and how much he is of a Statesman, by his Skilfullness in reading Faces. Your Honour will also see how earnest he is for Money, that he may resemble <hi>Soloman</hi> in Riches too; and by his Powerful Eloquence, Larded with a Hypocritical shew of Piety, he obtained a Second Tax of one Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a week for Thirteen weeks, to be Leyied on every Inhabitant in the Government, and their working Servants and Slaves: and this pretended, for carrying on the work of the Lord begun, that is the building and finishing the new Fort, on which, we do not know that one stroke of work hath been done, in the manner wherein it was begun▪ That Parliament find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Peoples money was not well laid out, made a Law, That whatsoever should be further done on the said Fort, should be by Advice of certain Persons nominated in the said Law; but, rather than Act by Advice and Council, he chose to do nothing to the Fort, but get the money into his own Hands, raised for that end, by the Assembly. But of late, of his own head (not only without, but against the Advice of the Council) he hath begun to Build a thing, more like a Cow-pen, than a Fort: whereon he hath spent much time, and (as we expect to find) much Money.</p>
               <p>I have also sent you a Petition, which was prepared to be presented to him, for the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning and Sitting of a General Assembly, which when he heard of, and the names of some of the Subscribers, he call'd them before him, and told them, by seting their names to that Petition, they were guilty of Treason, and had Forfeited their Lives, and Estates; and he might take away both at his pleasure. Some time after which, some of the most Consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inhabitants, as to Understanding, Ability, and Sobriety, with the Assistance of some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did Seize upon, and Restrain his Person, for a very short time, to reduce him, to more Reasonable proceedings. To which end we did make, and propose to him, some few and very mild Conditions of Peace, and Reconciliation which he then readily Accepted: whereupon he was restored, with Universal Expressions of Love and Respect; at which time he did publickly Acknowledge his Errors, with this Apology, (we are all Sinners, and that he was an Old Souldier, but a Young Governour,) and promised, That he would for the Future, do nothing of a publick Narure, without Advice: And for Uniting of all persons, and removing all Enmity, Malice, and Suspition, he would speedily Summon a Parliament, and have a General Act of Oblivion, prepared and passed. Soon after, a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was call'd; but at the time of the Election, by himself, and some of his Creatures, he so over rlul'd the Election, that he had a Parliament pack'd to his mind, which were absolutely Obsequious to his Dictates. The first thing offered in the said Parliament was a Bill for an Act of Oblivion, to which, tho in the upper House he seem'd inclinable; yet he had Engag'd a party in both Houses to oppose it: and so the intended Act, and the Parliament too, both came to nothing, only spent about Sixteen days in Wrangling, about the said Bill; which I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40621:5"/> have sent your Honour, according to your desire. I have also sent you a Coppy of the Lords Proprietors Instructions, that you may see how his Actions do square with their Rules, but that Parliament last mentioned, Frustrate of the good Designs and Desires of the Petitioners: the Countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y was left Groaning under the Languishing Distempers, which his Evil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had brought it into, and so hath continu'd Growing worse and worse. By the first Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, 'twas Enacted, <hi>That Coll.</hi> Bowen Clasen, <hi>should be Joyned with the Governour in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers Office; and that no Money belonging to the Publick Treasure should be Expended, without the Joynt consent of the Treasurers; and that their Accounts should be Audited every three Months.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing which Law, he hath taken upon him to demand and receive, all the publick Treasure from time, to time, not acquainting Coll. <hi>Bowen</hi> therewith; and as he receives, so he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burses according to his own pleasure; and his Accompts not submitted to an Audit since last <hi>July</hi> was a year; which is about Seventeen Months: And tho we have had but small occasion of publick Expences, since the last Tax was Granted, and he having received in Powder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey and Fort Money 121 <hi>l.</hi> as by Entries in the Book will appear: Yet he saith, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is Indebted to him Considerably; and as it fares with the Countries Treasure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o with the Lords Royalties▪ as we have good reason to Suspect. We cannot make a just Computation thereof, but guess upwards of 50 <hi>l.</hi> for fifths of <hi>Ambergrease:</hi> He hath so managed the publick Treasure, that he expects (if a General Assembly do sit) he shall be turned out of that Office; therefore he is as much appalled at the mention of a Parliament, and the coming of a new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, as <hi>Felix</hi> was, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> reasoned with him, <hi>Of Judgment to come.</hi> Through the perswasion of Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> (when here) he was prevailed upon, tho with great Reluctancy, to call a General Assembly, which was to sit the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>August</hi> last, but was by him (out of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse humour) Prorogu'd till the <hi>15th</hi> of the said Month: After we had sate a few days (which were spent in frivolous Disputes raised by himself (as we have reason to think) on purpose to waste time, and interupt business of Importance, which before we could fix upon, we were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily diverted, by some <hi>French</hi> Privateers, by whom we were in great danger of being taken and Plunder'd; and they lay so long just at our doors, that being tyred with continual watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing night and day; and our Planting the mean while neglected: For general ease, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Adjourn'd to the <hi>5th</hi> of this Month, at which time they were Adjourn'd to the <hi>7th Ditto,</hi> and then (by him) were Disolved, having passed but two Acts, one for Appointing the Court of Pleas, the other for punishing Idle persons. By what hath been rehearsed, your Honour may perceive▪ how he consumes the publick Stock, that should be Improved for publick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and thereby we are laid open and naked to the Common Enemy; from whose Invasion, our preservation (next to Divine protection) is to be Attributed to our poverty; we not being thought worth making an Attempt upon: And whereas in regard we are so Unfortified▪ it is highly necessary that our small strength should be United and Compacted▪ as much as may be; yet contrary to all rules of prudence, pollicy, and self-preservation, and the frequent Advice of the Wisest amongst us, he suffers about a 100 Men to live scattering about, among the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Islands; and not only suffers them to live after that manner, that the Government hath no benefit of them, nor they of the Government, but he strenuously Opposeth their coming hither; and at the Salt Season, permits all the people (in a manner) to desert this Island to go to the Salt Ponds, whereby we are exposed to be an Easiy Prey to the Common Enemy: And as if he design'd to Betray us into their Hands, he takes none (or very little) care for Amuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; so that many times, we have not enough to furnish the people, with s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ix Rounds for small Armes, and less for the great Guns, of which there are but three at present useful; and tho we are generally so bare, yet hath he either given or sould Gun Powder out of the Countries Stock, to Privateers; and sent away one of the great Guns in a Bark, which (by base and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy means) he hath gotten part of. And in destributing the Lords Lands, he gives greater Portions by far to Idle Drones, who make no Improvement, than the Lords allow to the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st Industrious Planters; and at the same time denyeth many Laborious men any Land that lies convenient; whereby divers who came hither on purpose to Settle and Plant, have been so discouraged, as to depart again with Damage, and others who have staid long in hopes, are yet destitute: And he suffers Punch Houses to be kept in such an unlimited manner, that they do Devour the Fruits of the peoples labours, and thereby, and the Idle expence of their time; the Growth and Flourishing of the Settlement is greatly Obstructed. And he so much connives at, or rather incourageth Profaness and Debauchery, that we may fear Gods wrath, to break forth against us, in fome Tremendous Judgment. He himself keeping a Young Wench, which he calls his Miss, whose Father was a Notorious Pirate, and her Mother is a Punch House Keeper; his Disciple <hi>Lightwood</hi> (who came with him) hath kept a mans Wife (who made him his Attorney here) as his own, and by her he hath had three Bastards, two whereof were Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive-Twins. His Secretary <hi>Graves,</hi> who by him was made a Deputy to one of the Lords Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (having a Wife at <hi>London</hi>) for several years did live here in Adultery with a kind of a <hi>Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee,</hi> who was his Bought Servant, by whom he hath had three Bastards, and with whom he hath lived, till (being depriv'd Justly of his Secretaries Place) he thought fit to go home to <hi>England,</hi> to seek for new preferment. <hi>Mercier</hi> (another of the Lords Deputies) hath lived here, in a state
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40621:6"/> of separation from his wife (who is said to be at <hi>New Yorke</hi>) 4 or 5 years; great part of which time, he hath lived in Adultery with a Nasty Punk, which he took as a Servant, by whom he hath a Bastard living. And these and such like, have been his peculiar Privado's, and most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cabinet Councellers, by whom he hath carried on his Villanies, and supported himself therein hitherto. Right Honourable, to draw to a conclusion of this unpleasant task, wherein I have wearied my self with Writing, and perhaps may you with Reading, yet have I shew'd you but little, of what might be shew'd of his Folly, Frenzey, and Knavery, whereof he is a Composition; and tis hard to say which is the Predominant Ingredient. To be short, he is (on all accompts) Morrally Unquallified for Government, and a great Scandal to his Office, which caused one from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> to break forth into this Admiration, <hi>O monstrum horrendum,</hi> that such an Idiot should live among Men, especially be in Government, which Reflects great Dishonour upon the Lords, who sent, and Commissionated him; and may much more fill their Face<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with shame, who recomended him to them. By his own Letters and Journals, he hath made himself most Ridiculous Abroad, and Contemptible at Home. And now Sir, we have shewed you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Evil Tree, which bringeth forth Evil Fruit, like to <hi>Jeremiabs</hi> bad Figgs (which is worse then Barreness) it is with you whether that Sentence shall pass, <hi>viz. Cut it down, why combereth it the Ground, but if there were any hopes, that (by Diging about it, Dunging, or Pruning,) it might bring forth good Fruit:</hi> We would become Intercessors▪ and say, <hi>Lord, let it alone this Year.</hi> Sir, we are very sensible of the Infallible truth of that Saying of our Great Lord, and Master, <hi>That a House or Kingdom divided against it self, cannot stand;</hi> and we also remember that the same Infallible Truth saith, <hi>That Offences will come, but he Pronounceth the Wo against him by whom they come:</hi> And whether we have given the Cause, or taken offence without just Cause, we sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our Cause, and our Selves, to Gods Judgment, and yours; being and Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cribing our selves,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>(<hi>Right Honourable,</hi>)</salute>
                  <signed>Your Obliged Humble Servants
<list>
                        <item>Gilbert Ashley.</item>
                        <item>Bowen Clasen.</item>
                        <item>Thomas Bulkley.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEsides the Papers forementioned, I have herewith sent you same</hi> Memorials of his Miscarriages, <hi>Contained in</hi> 39 Articles, <hi>Coppy of a</hi> Mittimus; <hi>a</hi> Message <hi>from the Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> to him, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a</hi> Misdemeanour <hi>of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a</hi> Pirate, <hi>and his promise under Written; his Speech to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, when Debated with, for ordering</hi> Vessels <hi>to</hi> Enter <hi>and</hi> Clear, <hi>at the</hi> Adjacent Islands, <hi>contrary to</hi> Law; <hi>and also ordering the</hi> Tenths <hi>of</hi> Salt <hi>to be demanded as a</hi> Royalty, <hi>his</hi> Message <hi>to the</hi> People, <hi>when under</hi> Confinement <hi>on</hi> Board <hi>the Ketch</hi> Industry, <hi>in this</hi> Harbour; <hi>his</hi> Proposals <hi>to the last</hi> Assembly, <hi>for his</hi> Personal <hi>going out against the</hi> French; <hi>also a</hi> Message <hi>from him to the</hi> Commons, <hi>in the said</hi> Assembly, <hi>and their</hi> Answer. <hi>I Humbly Pray your Honour that these Papers sent to you, may be carefully kept, and (after your Perusal) return'd to,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours Humble Servant, Thomas Bulkley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="addendum">
               <p>
                  <hi>AS a Supplement to our Letter we Write this to Informe your Honour. That at this time, the Publick Store of Gun▪ Powder is not above Twelve Pounds, and that this day, by our Governours consent, (without advice of the Council) came into this Harbour a Pirate Ship of 18 Guns, and about 50 or 60 Men, their Commanders name is</hi> John Cross, <hi>said to be as notorious a Pirate as any that Roves on the Sea, one that dares not go into any</hi> English <hi>Port but this. The Night before he came in, our Governour went up a High Hill to look out for him, who was then out of sight, whereat he was more troubled than at the News of the Earth Quake in</hi> Jamaica, <hi>and the Fearful and Doleful Dessolation and Destruction made thereby; for he spent great part of that day after the sad news, in Merriment and Drinking. Since the said Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates coming in, he hath permitted them, to buy up all the Corne that Mr.</hi> Ireland <hi>had, of which the People of the Island were in great want.</hi> Ireland <hi>might have had a Piece of Eight</hi> per <hi>Bushel of the Isl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders▪ He also permitted them to receive on Board their Ship, Men under Arrest for Trespass; and two Men against whom I had obtained Judgment of Court, for Debts to the Value of</hi> 24 l. 18 s. 4 d. <hi>due by Bills of their Hands; and being on Board the said Ship, they bid Defiance, not only to their Cred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itors, but, the Government also, of which I have complained to him, but cannot have any Remedy.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>New-Providence, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 17th <hi>of</hi> December, 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Honours, as above said, T. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the First Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <div type="half_title">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40621:6"/>
               <p>A Pacquet of Intelligence FROM NEW-PROVIDENCE. In the Province of the <hi>BAHAMA</hi> Islands, in AMERICA. The Second PART. Contained in Three LETTERS, As followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An Abstract of a Letter from Collonel <hi>Phillip Ludwell,</hi> Governour of <hi>Carolina,</hi> to Collonel <hi>Cadwallader Jones,</hi> late Governour of the <hi>BAHAMA</hi> Islands: In Answer to Two Letters Received from the said <hi>Jones.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Have received two Letters from you, one dated the</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> January, <hi>the other the</hi> 3d <hi>of this Instant; I know not what to Answer to the first, the Contents of it passing my understanding. I must tell you, I think that Letter was an ill return for the Kindness I Offer'd you; If you would (as I desired) have fairly stated your Case, that I might have Indeavoured to Reconcile and Settle all matters, on a more steady Foundation than I perceive they are, either for the Lords, or Peoples Interest: But you say, for that reason (if one may call it reason) you withdrew your Pacquet; by which, I wish you could see who you hurt, me you cannot. But you proceed further to your Meditations, indeed I think it were better you laid aside your Contemplations in Divinity a little, and Studdied the Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks more; or else instead of those mistaken Furrows on your Back, and Load on your Shoulders, you will lay a Load on your self, that all the Friends you have will not be able to take off. Your last seems of another hew, which shews you to be of an unequal temper, but give me leave to tell you, I am of opinion (by what I see in your own Papers) your Troubles are made more then needed to be. I do not see that you Act as you ought, without doubt your Government has not been without some Irregularitys; but yet cannot possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly think th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> putting you from the Government, Imprisoning you, and taking the Administration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment on them, was well done, by those that did it. I am sorry to find your disorders run so high, as Charging with High Treason, as I perceive Mr.</hi> Bulkley <hi>and you do each other. What inconveniencys you may both draw on your selves, by thus sillily Charging each other, I know not; but sure I am, no good can come to either, by it. And now I must come to my last part, at present; which is, to desire you, and I do hereby Conjure, and Require you, that you do (on your part) lay by all Quarrels, and Anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssitiys; and carry all matters Fairly, and Quietly, as you ought; till the Lords Proprietors do send further Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40621:7"/> which I doubt not you will (in as short time as may be) receive from them. I am not for under hand Dealings, what ever you think; especially for Intercepting Letters, which is Complained of, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a Crime so Barbarous, that I could almost <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> soon forgive Murther; Nor will it be well taken any where. I hope you will take care that Letters go free, on both sides; or else Misunderstandings will arise, and increase; and all Commerce soon have an end. I shall say no more, but desire you to consider, that by these Discords, you do (not only) ruine the Lords Interest, but expose your selves, and all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of those Islands, as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prey, to any t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at will take you.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Dated <date>the <hi>27th</hi> of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <dateline>Receiv'd <date>the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>I am your Friend and Servant, Phillip Ludwell.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A LETTER from Coll. <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip Ludwell,</hi> Governour of <hi>Carolina,</hi> Superscribed, as followeth, <hi>viz. These for</hi> Thomas Bulkley, <hi>Esquire, at</hi> New-Providence.</head>
               <head type="sub">As a Rejoynder to the foregoing, and some other Letters, Written and sent to him from the said Island; by <hi>Gilbert Ashley, Bowen Clasen,</hi> and the said <hi>Thomas Bulkley.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have receiv'd several Letters from you, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elieve all you sent, and am very sorry to find Matters run to so high a pitch, as charging with High Treason, as I perceive the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and you do each other; which puts the matter out of my reach to Examine, without a special Order: But I must tell you, I think neither of you in the right way, that there has been failings on your Governours side. I do not at all doubt; but most certain I am, that the way that has been taken to rectifie those Errors, will never be Justified any where. I was in hopes, on the receipt of your first Letter, some good end might be put to it, but I see both sides Raging so unreasonably against each other, that my present hopes are very Remote; I am much of opinion it will appear at last, most of these Fewds have been rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and maintained, by some that wish well to neither: In the beginning whereof, I presume <hi>Clarks</hi> hand was not wanting as far as the Devil could help him; he has been Nibbling here in the same kind, and without doubt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> been a troublesome Fellow wherever he has been, and eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> willbe. Your Governour informes me, that <hi>Clark</hi> sent you word, I had promised him a Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, for you to be Governour; I have ordered <hi>Clark</hi> to be taxed with it, who positively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies any such thing: And I believe the Mutual Fears, and Jealosies, the Governour and you both seem to be Affected with, of the danger of each others Life, arise much from the same Springs, <hi>viz.</hi> Some that perhaps would be glad to be rid of you both, for I cannot think there can be any danger, from your selves, allowing but a very mean proportion of what Sence you may pretend to: But sure I am (by the Methods you take) you are in the ready way, not only to draw great Inconveniencys on your selves (whilst perhaps others laugh in their sleves at you both) but also to Ruin the whole Settlement, in these Dangerous times. I am very sorry the matter could not be so stated to me, that I might have indeavoured to settle Affaires on a more steady Foundation, than I perceive they are, or have been, either for the Interest of the Lords, or People, which I take to be Highly hazarded, by these Discords. If the state of the matter had come as it ought, I'le assure you I should have spared no Paines, Trouble, or Charge, to have reconciled them: But as it is, I must at present leave it to a farther inquiry, being not Possibly able (at this time) to come to you, which I should readily have done, but that my Affaires Unavoidably presses me to <hi>North-Carolina,</hi> and <hi>Virginia,</hi> for three or four Months at least: If I go not for <hi>England,</hi> of which I am not yet certain. In the mean time, all I can do, is to Desire, and I do hereby Earnestly Conjure, and Require you, that you cease from all Private Animossitys, and Quarrels, and mind the Preservation of the Publick, without tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little mean Advantages of Each other; but do you all Joyn up as one Man, for the Common good, till you hear from the Lords, who (I doubt not) will take all Just Measures, that every body may have Right; and I dare Ingage you shall hear with all the speed that may be: I hope those that took the Administration of the Government on them, has (ere this) considered bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Deliver'd it back into the Hand it ought to be, by the Lords Commission, till their farther Order; for certainly that Proceeding will not, cannot be Justified: Nor can I at all think your Requiring a Guard at the latter end of your Charge against Collonel <hi>Jones,</hi> was well done: But I suppose that, nor your other Papers, are not yet gone farther; and so I think your wisest way is, to shut up all, and bear with what Infirmities you see in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40621:7"/> and advise him for the Common Good, as I said before, till an enquiry can be made on the place, and all may possibly be well yet; but I am sure better that way then any you now take: Pray consider well what you do, of which I have the better hope, if you can guide your Passions as well as I see you can your Pen. The moving for Appointing a Council, was very Ill; being no more in your Power, then it was in those Gentlemen to appoint a Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the Governour being on the place: I hope you will excuse me for dealing thus plainly with you; I have dealt as plainly with your Governour, and for no other reason, but that you might rightly understand one another, and the Countrey be at Peace: that others may be Incouraged to come to you; to which end, I have desired the Governour to shew you what I have Writ him; and if you please to do the like to him, I think it would be very well: I have sent you back all your Papers, and thank you for your good Intentions in the <hi>Oranges;</hi> tho not one came, which ought not to lessen your kindness: Possibly you may hear from me again from hence, if not, tis ten to one the next you hear from me, will be from <hi>England,</hi> from whence (if I go) you will all hear from me. Pray remember what I tell you, let no Indeavours of yours be wanting to keep all in Peace; from whence (believe me) you will Reap the greatest Advantage. I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Carolina,</hi>
                     <date>Febr. <hi>27th</hi> 1692.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  <signed>Your Friend and Humble Servant, Phillip Ludwell.</signed>
               </closer>
               <argument>
                  <p>I have not seen the Articles of High Treason on either side, and so can say nothing to them. You Complain of Intercepting of Letters, and so do's the Governour; I know not which side, or whether both are Guilty; but it is certainly a Crime of so Base and Barbarous a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that any thing less <hi>Savage</hi> then an <hi>Indian,</hi> would Abhor it. Pray let there be no more cause of such Complaints among you; it will make all People shy of Corresponding with you.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A LETTER from</hi> Thomas Bulkley <hi>of</hi> New-Providence, <hi>Merchant, (being a Prisoner under the Tyrannical and Ʋsurped Power of</hi> Cadwallader Jones, <hi>who was Accused of High Treason, and many othes Capital Crimes, by the said</hi> Bulkley <hi>as Prosecutor for the King, and Lords Proprietors; and [by the Council of the Province] Confined to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Law; but was Rescued out of Custody by a party of Impudent Rogues, Pirates,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>Superscribed,</hi> To the Right Honourable Collonel <hi>Phillip Ludwel,</hi> Governour of Carolina. <hi>As a Surreioynder to his Letters foregoing.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOURS bearing date the <hi>27th</hi> of <hi>October</hi> in Answer to mine, dated the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> Subscribed by Mr. <hi>Gilbert Ashley,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Bowen Clasen,</hi> (being two of the Lords Proprietors Deputies) and my self, Confirmed in us all, an opinion, that you had Authority to inquire into the Constitution and Administration of our Government; and to rectifie the Errors which do abound in both, through the evil Conduct of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. To which (upon Receipt of our Complaints) in your first Letter to us, you seem'd very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable, only you desir'd (first) a clearer Information of the Fundamental causes, which were largely set forth unto you, in sundry Letters, and Papers, sent to you by Mr. <hi>Irelands</hi> Vessels In which you had such a Representation of the Multipli'd, Follys, and Roguerys of Coll. <hi>Jones,</hi> (in the Instances whereof, we were so far from exceeding, that without an <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> I may say we did not charge him with one of an Hundred; nor did we, nor could we set them out in their Native Deformity, in regard of their Circumstantial Aggravations) as we thought would have kindled in your Breast a just Indignation against him, and have Excited you to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of your Promise, in the Postscript of your Letter, in these words, <hi>viz. (If nothing will do, but my coming, that shall not be wanting, as soon as ever I can settle matters here, which I hope are now in a fair way</hi>) whereof we had Pregnant hopes, and my House being thought the fitest for your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; I did put my self and Wife to no small Trouble, and Charge to prepare for your Reception; which was not upon any information from Mr. <hi>Clarke,</hi> of his being promised by you a Commission for me to be Governour, that was a shameless Lye of <hi>Jones</hi>'s own Inventing; but is not the first (by some Hundred of Lyes) that he hath Forgod of me; and such I suppose are most if not all his Complaints to you against me: And indeed, like those rulers in <hi>Isaiah</hi> the 28. <hi>c. 15. v. He makes Lyes his Refuge, and hiding Place; which I hope God will sweep away with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40621:8"/> his Threatned Judgment, v.</hi> 17. For your Conviction, that Mr. <hi>Clarke</hi> Writ not any such thing to me, as <hi>Jones</hi> hath informed you; I shall send you the only Letter that ever I received from him, who (however he hath carried himself in <hi>Carolina</hi>) when here, was so far from being a Disturber of the Peace, that he was a great Peace-maker; and therein he was Officious almost beyond what prudence and Justice would admit, particularly in Mediating a Reconciliation between <hi>Jones</hi> and my self, who were at Variance when he came; tho that (being Hypocritical on <hi>Jones</hi>'s part) was of short continuance; nor is any peace to be held with him, but by an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of his vile practices, and a Consociation with him therein. Sir, it seems strange to us, that such Capital Crimes as he stands Charg'd with, (not against particular Persons only, but the whole Interest of the Lords, and People, as to their Lives Liberties and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,) should be termed Failings and Infirmitys, which we should bear with, and Advise him to better Courses. Sir, we say we have born long, not with Infirmities only, but with grose Enormities, in which he hath exercised himself ever since he came to the Government, which is now more then two Years, and three Quarters; and that is a long tract of time, for one that hath such a strong bent of inclination to all that is Vile, and detestable; and a conceite that he is not at all liable to the Coactive Power of the Law: If good advice could have had any Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy (by informing his Understanding, to have Reformed his Practice) we should not have used such methods as we have with him, nor complain'd to you: But his Errors proceed not so much from want of knowledge, as pravity of will, and affections, which makes him Obstinate, and fills him with-Malignity against such as express a dislike of his Courses, insomuch that he makes it his business to traduce them, with false Accusations, at home, and abroad; and is rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less till he hath gotten them out of all places of Power, or Trust, and Capacity of Living on the place. You say you are certain that the way that hath been taken to rectifie his Errors, will not, cannot be justified, any where; As to which, I shall crave leave to tell you, that I am of a contrary opinion, and will venture to Vindicate them before the Strictest Tribunal on Earth, which I long to appear before, for that end; which was the reason that we addressed our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to you, who (we thought) was every way quallified to be a Judge, from whom we expected a just and speedy Decision; but (to our great dissapointment, and grief) you have declin'd so good a work, wherein the Honour of God, and of their Majesties, and the Interest of the Lords Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etors, and the Safety and Tranquillity of the People, is greatly concerned; and whereby you would have procured to your self the Blessings of the Oppressed; which <hi>Job</hi> (that incomparable Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate of his time) set a High value upon, and much Gloried in, <hi>c. 29. v.</hi> 11, 12. And indeed a Virtuous Man, takes it as a great a Favour of God, when he puts Power, and an Oppertunity into his hand, to Relieve the Oppressed; than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich, there is not a more Honourable and Praise-worthy Work, that a Man can be imployed in. Sir, you say you were in hopes to have reconciled our Differences, (which ariseing from such causes as you have been made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with) you might as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Nature. You say if the State of the Matter had come to you as it ought, you would have Spared no Pains, Trouble, and Charge, to have Reconciled them. Sir, How you would have had it come, we cannot apprehend: You desired to know the Grounds of our Discontents, and Complaints, which in the Letters, and other Papers, was Plentifully Communicated to you; and (as we think) with a Competent measure of Humble Respect to you, and Submission to to your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: If you thought our Animadvertions on him, and his Actions, too Sharp; it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you wanted some Degrees of a due Measure of Sympathy with us, under our Intollerable Pressures. And I believe our Proceedings towards <hi>Jones,</hi> may be much better Vindicated, than for any Governour, that hath Authority and Power to Relieve his Majesties Subjects (upon Complaint made to him) to let them lye Groaning under such Insuportable Grievances, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to the Rage of a Detestable Traytor and Tyrant. The Distempets of our Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique are such as do affect the Vital parts with Strong Convultions, and therefore require a speedy application; Which makes us wonder that our Extraordinary Physitian should Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe a Remedy, that in all Humane Probability cannot be had till long after the Patient is Dead; I mean waiting to hear from the Lords Proprietors. Sir, You seem very much to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve of his being Sequester'd from the Administration of the Government, tho Accused of High Treason, contain'd in Sundry Articles; which (in the Judgment of Humane Laws) is the greatest Crime that can be Committed, and advise the Reinstateing him therein; as if it were impossible for him (having a Commission to be Governour) by any Crimes whatsoever, to forfeit his Right of Government: But I am perswaded, that you cannot produce one presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of any Person Invested with any Office of Power, and Trust, that (being Accused of High Treason) did continue in the Administration thereof, after such Accusation, till clear'd by due Process of Law. And if you duly consider the Formidable Consequences thereof, you will Retract such Advice (some of which I shall present you with.) Sir, You seem to pass a Censure of Blame on those that Sequester'd him from the Administration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and took it on themselves, in that you say, you hope they have better Consider'd, and Deliver'd it back to him, having the Lords Commission. I suppose they did well consider before they Acted, and did apprehend it to be (not only Warrantable, but) their bounden
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40621:8"/> Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, to Suspend him from the Administration of the Government, being accused of High Treason in sundry particulars, whereby he was Legally Disabled, until Cleared by Law. And the Dangerous consequences, that rationally may be expected to be the Issue of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, or Reinvestiture, are sufficient Arguments against both; for thereby he will be in a capacity to go on in his Tyrannical and Traiterous Practices, to the further Ruin of the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, and Inhabitants; especially those who Opposed him, in his Nefarious Practices, and Plots; whose Lives, and Estates, will be exposed to his Revengeful Malice: And when he hath Committed all the Villanies that his Savage Cruelty of Disposition will Prompt him unto, and suspects to be Called to acount for the same. He may do, as (about five Months after his comming) he said be would in case the Lords should send for him home, <hi>viz. That he would go amongst the</hi> Spaniards <hi>at the</hi> Havanna; and then where shall sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>faction be had for those Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Rapines that he shall commit in that time; but prevention is better than remedy. And tho you think that my Fears as to my self, and the danger of my Life, by reason of his Malice, is Groundless, and Senceless; yet when I shall have related to you, what hath been Acted since I Wrote last to you, you will see cause to think as I did, and do; which said Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative please to take as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> The general Impeachment (which you have seen) was delivered to Coll. <hi>Bowen Clasen,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gilbert Ashley,</hi> the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> and by them Communicated to the Council imediately; and upon Reading thereof, <hi>Jones</hi> was Seized, and made acquainted with the Impeachment against him; which (at first) he made light of, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He had intended to Impeach me;</hi> But after one nights Consideration thereof, he was greatly Dejected, and the next day desired three of the Council, to come to me, and acquaint me, that he desir'd that he might Discourse with me at my House, which they having consented to, I did not refuse; So he came to my House, and in the presence of five Members of the Council, he did earnestly Solicit me, to desist further Proceeding on my Accusation; and (that all matters of difference might be Silently Composed) he promised that whatsoever was amiss in his Management of the Government, should for the future be amended; and that he would Restore me to my Offices, from which (by his Procurement) I was unjustly Suspended, and that he wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d make me such Reparation of the Injuries done to me, as I should desire, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Ability: And in his future Conduct of the Government, he would be directed by me, and every thing should be managed according to my will, and desire; at the same time he acknowledged many Errors, but pleaded Ignorance as an excuse for all. After about three hours spent in discourse of this Nature, he went home, just before his departure, desireing me to promise him that I would consider of matters to his Advantage; and asked if he might not Visit me the next Morning, to the same end, which (it being the Lords day) I refused, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he proposed the Evening of the same day, which I yeelded to: Accordingly he came, soon after his coming, my Wife entered into a serious debate with him, Inquiring what was the reason of his Cruel Malice against me, instancing in sundry Particulars thereof, to which he replied, that I had crossed him, she asked wherein, he said in hindring him of the Tenths of Salt; and she taxing him with writing a Letter to <hi>Cross,</hi> and his Company of Pirates, he would have Evaded an answer to that, but she held him so close to the question, that at last she wrung out of him a Confession, that he did send a Note to the said <hi>Cross,</hi> which (he said) was only that they might justifie him, as to an Aspersion that had been cast on him by some, who had reported that he had given them a Commission, when they were here before. Much other discourse passed on both sides, till it grew late in the Night, when (being about to depart) he desired to know the result of my Consideration, as to his former desires, which I told him, I could not comply with, having accused him of such Crimes, as were Unpardonable. by any except their Majesties, and that by withdrawing my Accusation, and privately Shuffling up such Heinous Offences; I should make my self Guilty of Misprision of Treason, and thereby incur such Penalties, as I had no reason to do, for the nearest and dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Friend in the World, much less for my Mortal Enemy: Whereupon he said, will you have my Harts Blood then, and so (without any more but good night) he departed with his man <hi>Robert Bolion,</hi> who waited on him both times of his coming. On <hi>Monday</hi> Morning the <hi>23d.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> the said Accusation was Publickly Read in the Town, and I required by the Council to give Bond of 500 <hi>l.</hi> to Prosecute him upon the Impeachment, and on the <hi>1st.</hi> day of <hi>February,</hi> to produce particular Aritcles to make good the General Accusation, both which I did, and delivered the Articles in Council on the day appointed, where they were read; after which one <hi>Martin Cock</hi> (lately a Tapster at a Rum-Punch-House, but newly made a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty to one of the Lords Proprietors) in <hi>Jones</hi>'s behalf, asked for a Coppy of the Articles; which being denyed, as a thing neither Usual, nor Propper; and being told that (he sitting there as a Proprietors Deput), and <hi>Jones</hi> Accused of High Crimes and Misdemeanours, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted against the Lords) it did ill become him to make such a Motion: He immediately start<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and went out, rudely saying, a Fart for you all; whereupon Coll. <hi>Bowen Clasen</hi> (taking it as an Intollerable Affront) went after him, and gave him two or three Cuffs, and a Kick, and so left him. Away goes <hi>Cock</hi> to <hi>Jones,</hi> and his Confederates, tells them what Coll. <hi>Bowen Clasen</hi> had done to him; whereupon <hi>Daniel Jackson</hi> (a Pirate, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me in here with one Captain
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40621:9"/>
                  <hi>Woollery,</hi> whose Name is much known in <hi>Carolina,</hi> and most parts of <hi>America,</hi> and who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of <hi>Jones</hi>'s Deputies) came out, and with his Sword drawn, Presented the Point to Coll. <hi>Bowens</hi> Breast, requiring him to draw, which he (considering the Dangerous consequence thereof) refused to do: <hi>Jackson</hi> (with many Bloody Oaths, and Horrid Imprecations) said, he would have the Souls of some of us; and that (if he had his Western Men of whom <hi>Jones</hi> had newly made him Captain) he would drive us all to the Devil. Mr. <hi>Ashley</hi> (who was Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident of the Council) required him in their Majesties Name to keep the Peace; To which he reply'd, That he would not obey his Commands, and they were Fools that would; and call'd out, Who is for <hi>Jackson,</hi> whereupon two Men came forth as Abettors to him, in his Seditious Actions, but none appeared to Suppress them. At last (with much perswasion of Coll. <hi>Bowen) Jackson</hi> was a little cooled, but by his Hectoring, <hi>Martin Cock</hi> was Imboldned to give Coll. <hi>Bowen,</hi> and President <hi>Ashley,</hi> most Abusive and Provoking Language, and to Challange them. By this their Insolent and Seditious Behaviour, I was in great danger of being Assaulted, by two Lewd and Impudent Women, the one being <hi>Jacksons</hi> Wife, the other <hi>Graves</hi>'s Whore, from whom I was forc'd Patiently to take very Abusive Language. This days work brake the Council in pieces, so that they could not proceed to Settle the Government, nor do any thing tending thereunto; whereby all our Laws (according to the Lords Proprietors Rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) did Expire, they allowing them to continve but Two Years, unless Ratified by their Assent, which none of ours were; So, Eight Days after this Combusion, our Laws did give up the Ghost. The next day after the said Uprore, <hi>Jones</hi> (who had been Limitted to his House from <hi>Monday</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> of <hi>January</hi> till then) presum'd to set himself at Liberty, and to go where he pleased; and held divers Consults with his Cabal of Plotters; the result where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was, That (on <hi>Monday</hi> the <hi>27th.</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi>) the said <hi>Daniel Jackson,</hi> and one <hi>Thomas Witter,</hi> (a Shoemaker belonging to <hi>Barmudus,</hi> but resident here for about Twelve Months, yet no Free-holder; Nevertheless a little before made a Captain by <hi>Jones) Thomas Wake,</hi> (a <hi>Jamaica</hi> Pirate,) <hi>Martin Cock, Thomas Cumber,</hi> (another Deputie, made of an Ejected Representative) <hi>Bartholomew Mercier,</hi> (a Native <hi>Frenchman</hi> who in the year 1688. or 89. was Leader of a Party of Men who Robbed, some <hi>French Protestants,</hi> who had fled for Religion from some of the <hi>French Plantations,</hi> and were Bound for <hi>Carolina;</hi> but their Vessel proving Leaky, they came to the West end of this Island to repair the same, where being descried by some of our People, Information was given of them, and a Party sent to discover who they were, who after dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with them, return'd with the account aforesaid, <hi>viz. That they were Fugitive</hi> French <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants for Religion,</hi> which satisfied the People; But not <hi>Mercier,</hi> who got together about 14 men, most of which were Pirates, with these, he Marched to them again, on pretence of not being sufficiently satisfied concerning them; but the true reason was to Share their Money, which they did (by force of Armes, with threatnings of Death) compel them to part with, to the Valve of 1600 Pieces of Eight, besides Gold: as I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Informed. This Fact is well known to many in <hi>Carolina,</hi> some or the wronged Persons being there, as I have heard; the greatest looser was <hi>Monsieur Balle.) George Dumarisque</hi> (who is Marshal, and a Countrey Representative, so made, by <hi>Jones</hi>'s Pact Parliament) and <hi>Robert Bolton, Jones</hi> Foot Boy; These together with a parcel of the Seduced and Deluded Rabble, gathered together, and in a most Seditious mannerbrought forth <hi>Jones,</hi> demanded his Armes, and Papers, of Coll. <hi>Bowen Clasen,</hi> (in whose Custody they were) threatning that if they had them not, they would pull down his House, which they Forceably enter'd, and there took what they pleased: Then Re-esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished <hi>Jones</hi> as Governour: <hi>Jackson</hi> at the same time declaring, That tho they had Restor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d him to the Government, yet he was their Prisoner: After this, <hi>Jackson, Cock, Witter,</hi> and <hi>Bolton,</hi> with about 9 of the Mobile-Vulgus (in a Riotous and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ditious Manner) came to my House, of which (for my safety) I had shut up the Doors, Locking and Bolting them; when they came up to the House, I Spake to them through the Window, demanding what was their business, <hi>Jackson</hi> answer'd that they were come for the Countreys Books of Records, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I told them I had not any Books of the Countreys, tho I had the Books which contain'd the Records, and other Publick Concernments of the Country, and that they were my Propper Charge, committed to my Trust by Major <hi>Holloway,</hi> with the Approbation of the Council; and that 1000 <hi>l.</hi> Bond was given as Security for my Fidelity in the Secretarys Office, which I had by Deputation from Major <hi>Holloway,</hi> to whom I had given a Receipt for the Books which were propperly his, being Purchased by him with his Money; and it would be a Breach of Trust and Obligation in me, to deliver them, unless Legally demanded: They said they were the Countrys, and as such they demanded them, and would have them; I told them, I should not deliver them on that pretence, whereupon <hi>Jackson</hi> took up a Log of Timber, and therewith Brake open the back Door, which had Iron Hinges, and an Iron Bolt, and he and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany forceably enter'd the House, Reitterating their demands, which still I refused to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with; whereupon they said they would break every Lock in the House for them, and if they got them not, they would Burn the House: I told them if they did, I could not help it, for I was not able to resist them. They Searched several Chests, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not finding them, they said they would carry me away with them, and keep me a Prisoner, till I would deliver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40621:9"/> them, which they imediately did, setting a Guard of three Armed-Men upon my House, and brought me as a Malefactor before <hi>Jones</hi> (that Vile Traytor against whom I had then Exhibited Articles of High Treason) who presently apply'd himself to draw a Warrant for my Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Prison, which was directed to divers of the aforenamed Persons; by Virtue of which I was shut up in a Room of a House, whereof <hi>Jones</hi>'s Miss, her Mother, was owner; and after I had been there some time, I was visited by some of my Goalers, who came to see if I would submit to their demands, but I still persisting in my denial, they threatned me with the <hi>Strap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pado:</hi> I told them the Laws of <hi>England</hi> did prohibit Torturing the greatest Criminal, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it would be Barbarous Cruelty to deale so with an Innocent Man, for his Fidelity to his Trust. I also demanded (in their Majesties name) a Coppy of the Warrant for my Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but could not obtaine it: They left me again for a short time, and then came and ask'd me, if I would send home an Order, for delivery of the Books, I answer'd I would not do it, then they told me they would keep me there, without Meat, Drink, or any other of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Refreshments of Nature, and I should lye on the Bare Boards; so they nailed up the Window Shutters, which made the Roome like a Dungeon, without Light, or Air, except a very little which came through the Crevices of the Shutters, whereby (the Roome being newly Plaster'd and the Weather very hot) I was like to faint: After I had been in this stifeling condition a while, they came to me again, and told me they would (on delivery of the Books) give me up the Security bond, pay me Five Pounds for the Books, and release me from my Imprisonment; to which Proposals (finding that for want of Air, I could not Live in that Condition Twelve Hours) I yeelded, to save my Life: But they perform'd not what they offer'd. So I was conducted home with a Guard, and deliver'd the Books; after which, <hi>Witter</hi> (who Commanded the Party) demanded the Rolles of Laws, made in our first General Assembly, which were then expired: I told him they were of no more use than an old Almanack, that they were my Labour, in the Proposeing, Frameing, and Writing, for which I was never paid any thing by the Country: And if I was not worthy of Civil Respect and trust by them, they were not worthy of the Fruit of my Paines and Labours; Nor was I obliged by promise to deliver them, neither were they expressed in his Written Order. Then <hi>Witter</hi> told me, They would carry me Prisoner back again; rather then which (it being very late, I very ill, and my Lodging like to be so very bad) against my Reason and Inclination I yeelded to his unreasonable demands. The next day <hi>Jones</hi> with his Juncto of Traytors, and Rebbells, sat in Council, and Passed some Orders, which they call'd Laws, one whereof was, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Ashley, <hi>Coll.</hi> Bowen, <hi>and my self, should be Ejected out of our Respective Offices, and be for ever uncapable of any Office in the Grvernment.</hi> Two or three days after, all these Ruffians, (except two) with almost all the men belonging to the Island, went away to the Salt Ponds, leaving it Naked and Desti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute of Defence, although <hi>Jones</hi> was inform'd lately from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> did intend to giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother visit this Summer▪ and therefore was advis'd to prepare for them. I am inform'd that <hi>Jones</hi> hath wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Deputy Governour of <hi>Xuma</hi> (being one of the adiacent Islands, where is the principal Salt Pond, and greatest resort of ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels) that in Case <hi>Ashley, Bowen,</hi> or I, should come thither, with design to go off, we should be stopt; the like (I suppose) he hath written to other Places. Now Sir, by what hath been related, which is real matter of Fact, you may see what desperate Villains we have amongst us, and those introduced into Places of Power by <hi>Jones,</hi> on purpose to support him, and assist him, in his Arbitrary and Tyrannical Government, and to crush all those which do oppose it, tho in Just and Lawful ways; and what great reason I had to demand a Guard for my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. Truly Sir, I have been so horribly abused and threatned by Pirates, and Lewd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that are his Favorites and Adherents, that I have been Little Better than a Prisoner to my House, for near Four Months; and there not in safety, not dareing to go about my Lawful and necessary Occasions, nor can I get in any Debts, whereof I have many out-standing, whereby I and my Family are like to be R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>duced to terrible Extremities, unless God (who pleadeth the Cause of the Oppressed) do send speedy deliverance. It is a most Heart-cutting Consideration, that a man (for no other cause, but his Zealous standing up for the interest of the Lords Proprietors, and the Safety and Liberty of the People) shall be exposed to the Barbarous rage of Execrable Traytors, and Rebbels, and no remedy to be had, nor any way to escape, that Application may be made where Justice may be had, which is that I desire, and (seeing it is not to be had in the Derivatives) I will (if possible) repaire to the Fountaine, tho I Wade through the Greatest Diffiiculties. You say my moving for appointing a Council was very Ill, it being no more in my power, then in the Councils to appoint a President. Sir, In answer to that, I say I did it not as an Act of Power, but by way of Advice, for common safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and tho it were a Deviation from the Letter of the Lords Instructions, yet was it agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Spirit and Design of them, which without doubt was the Safety and Prosperity of the Settlement, which the most Virtuous and Discreet men are more likely Instruments to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, than a parcel of Sea and Land-Robbers, Whoremongers, Blasphemers, Horrible Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Drunkards, of which sort were 8 of the 12 Counfellors; and I Suppose such shall be chosen to fill up the places of Mr. <hi>Ashley</hi> and Coll. <hi>Bowen,</hi> turn'd out: Therefore I think it was not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40621:10"/> very ill, but very well done of me, to propose a Reformation; and for which (when the Lords Proprietors know it) I expect their thanks. I am confident if they had imagined that <hi>Jones</hi> would have so vilely Prostituted the Power, and Honour, which they had intrusted him with the distribution of; they would have thought him unworthy to bear any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of himself. Sir, You say that you take the Interest of the Lords and People to be Highly Hazarded by the Discords between him and me, if you had said by the Causes, (his Misgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) you had hit the Mark, <hi>viz.</hi> Consumeing on his Lusts, the Publick Treasure, which should have been laid out in Fortification, and Amunition, letting the Timber (which with much Toyle and Charge was Saw'd and brought out of the Woods for Carriages of Guns) lye Rotting on the Ground, not converting it to the use for which it was provided, but either Selling or Giving it away; letting great Guns lye Useless in the Sea, and se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding others off, when for want, he had fent for two from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> which after they came, lay about 12 Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Sea; and whereas there was 5 Mounted whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Extravagant manner; so that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we have not had suffici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ree Rounds; permitting the People to Live Scattering in the Adjacent Islands, contrary to Law, and all the Political ends of Humane Society; enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Pirates, and Granting them Commissions, whereby the Place is become a mear Den of Thieves; Tollerating, yea Countenancing all manner of Profaness and Debauchery, and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging all Piety and Morality, to the High Displeasure of Almighty God, and great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Place, and People inhabiting the same: These are the things that hazard the Lords Interest, and the Peoples, and these are the Grounds of our Controversies, and Contests with him, and not (as you seem to apprehend) little Piques, and Animosities; and of these, and such like, I have mildly told him, and Advised otherwise, but to no Purpose: I have told him after this manner, <hi>Sir, Act in your Place as becomes a Man of Honour, and Honesty, and you shall always find me ready to serve you, with the respect that is due to your Place; but if you will En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage your self in things that are Base, and Vile, you must not expect me to joyne with you.</hi> Which my Disapprobation of his Roguish Practices, and Discention from him, and his Ignorant and Wicked Confederates, hath brought me into this Deplorable Condition, wherein I now am, destitute of all Humane Relief, and exposed to the Inveterate and Exasperated Malice of my Mortal Enemy, who will not be Satisfied with any thing less then my Person for a Bloody Sacrifice, which, (if the great Preserver and Deliverer of those who are appointed to Dye, do not wonderfully prevent) I am design'd by him, and do expect to be made. But before I Dye, I bequeath to you (as a Memorial) the <hi>11th</hi> and <hi>12th</hi> Verses, of the <hi>24th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Solomans Proverbs,</hi> viz. <hi>If thou forbear to deliver them that are ready to be Slain; If thou sayest, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold we knew it not, doth not he that Poridereth the Heart consider it; and he that keepeth thy Soul, doth not he know it; and shall not he render to every Man, according to his works.</hi> Which Text (so often as you Read it) will bring to your Remembrance, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Majesties, and the Lords Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etors Martyr, who (on their behal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as well as his own) was once</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>New Providence, <date>
                        <hi>the 20th of</hi> May, 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Humble Orator, Thomas Bulkley.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Part.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>